As a child,
عندما كنت صغيرة
I was raised by native Hawaiian elders --
كان يشرف على تربيتي
three old women
3 نسوة من اهل "هاواي" المحلين
who took care of me while my parents worked.
عندما كان والدي يذهبان الى العمل
The year is 1963.
في عام 1963
We're at the ocean.
كنا على جانب البحر
It's twilight.
في وقت الشفق
We're watching the rising of the stars
وكنا نشاهد النجوم
and the shifting of the tides.
والتحول بين المد والجذر
It's a stretch of beach we know so well.
انه مشهد خلاب يشاهد عند الشاطىء ..
The smooth stones on the sand
نعرفه جميعاً .. لمعان الصخور ..و الرمال
are familiar to us.
انه امرٌ نعرفه جميعاً
If you saw these women on the street
ان رأيت أؤلئك النسوة في الطريق
in their faded clothes,
في ملابسهن الفضفاضة
you might dismiss them
سوف تظن أنهن ..
as poor and simple.
فقيرات وبسيطات
That would be a mistake.
وهذا ظنٌ خاطىء
These women are descendants
ان هذه النسوة هنَّ
of Polynesian navigators,
احفاد الملاحين البولينيزية
trained in the old ways
تم تدريبهن
by their elders,
بواسطة اجدادهن على الطريقة القديمة
and now they're passing it on to me.
والآن هن ينقلن علومهنَّ إلي
They teach me the names of the winds and the rains,
فهنَّ يعلمونني اسماء الرياح والامطار
of astronomy according to a genealogy of stars.
وعلم الفلك نسبة الى علم انساب النجوم
There's a new moon on the horizon.
هناك قمرٌ جديد في الافق ..
Hawaiians say it's a good night for fishing.
سكان هاواي .. يقولون هذه العبارة في ليالي الصيد الجيدة
They begin to chant.
انهم يرنمون ..
[Hawaiian chant]
ترنيمة من هاواي
When they finish,
عندما ينتهون
they sit in a circle
يجلسون في دائرة
and ask me to come to join them.
وطلبوا مني الحضور ذات يوم
They want to teach me about my destiny.
وقاموا باخباري عن مصيري
I thought every seven-year-old went through this.
واعتقد ان كل فتاة عمرها 7 سنوات تسمع هذا الكلام
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"Baby girl,
"طفلتي العزيزة ..
someday the world will be in trouble.
يوما ما سوف يغدو هذا العالم قاس ..
People will forget their wisdom.
سوف يفقد الناس حكمتهم
It will take elders' voices
وسوف يتحتم على اصوات الاجداد
from the far corners of the world
من حولنا في كل بقاع الارض
to call the world into balance.
ان تدعوا العالم الى التوازن
You will go far away.
سوف تذهبين بعيداً
It will sometimes be a lonely road.
سوف تسيرين على الدرب وحيدة بعض الأحيان
We will not be there.
لن يكون احد بقربك
But you will look into the eyes
ولكنك سوف تتلاقين بالاعين
of seeming strangers,
مع شخص يبدو غريباً
and you will recognize your ohana,
ولكن سوف تميزين فوراً " الاوهانا "
your family.
عائلتك
And it will take all of you.
وسوف يأسرك تماما
It will take all of you."
سوف يأسرك ! "
These words, I hold onto
هذه الكلمات .. التزمت بها
all my life.
طيلة حياتي
Because the idea of doing it alone
لان فكرة العيش وحيدة
terrifies me.
كانت تخيفني جداً
The year is 2007.
في عام 2007
I'm on a remote island in Micronesia.
كنت على جزيرة معزولة في ميكرونيسيا
Satawal is one half-mile long
جزيرو ساتاوال .. هي بطول نصف ميل
by one mile wide.
وبعرض ميل واحد
It's the home of my mentor.
انها موطن مرشدي
His name is Pius Mau Piailug.
اسمه " بيس بيايلوج "
Mau is a palu,
"ماو" .. هو من سلالة "بولو"
a navigator priest.
انه راهب متجول
He's also considered
وهو ايضاً يُعد
the greatest wave finder in the world.
امهر من يجد الموجات في العالم
There are fewer than a handful
وقد تبقى القليل فحسب
of palu left on this island.
من سلالة " بولو " على تلك الجزيرة
Their tradition is so extraordinary
ان تقاليدهم مميزة جداً
that these mariners sailed
ان هؤلاء البحارة يبحرون
three million square miles across the Pacific
في مساحة 3 ملاين متر مربع في المحيط الهادىء
without the use of instruments.
بدون اي من ادوات الملاحة
They could synthesize patterns in nature
ويمكنكم تنسيق منحى تحركهم
using the rising and setting of stars,
بواسطة مواقع وحركات النجوم
the sequence and direction of waves,
وتتابع حركات الامواج
the flight patterns of certain birds.
واتجاهات هجرة الطيور
Even the slightest hint of color
وحتى التغير البسيط
on the underbelly of a cloud
في ألوان السحب في السماء
would inform them
يمكنها ان تدلهم
and help them navigate with the keenest accuracy.
وتساعدهم على الابحار بدقة
When Western scientists would join Mau on the canoe
عندما سيرافق العلماء الغربيون " ماو " في احد الزوارق
and watch him go into the hull,
ويراقبونه كيف يدخل الى بدن الزورق
it appeared that an old man
حيث ربما سيبدو لهم ان الرجل العجوز
was going to rest.
محتاج للراحة
In fact, the hull of the canoe
بينما في الحقيقة .. ان بدن الزورق
is the womb of the vessel.
هو رحم الزورق
It is the most accurate place
انه اكثر مكان يمكن بدقة فيه
to feel the rhythm and sequence
استشاعر تتابع وتناغم
and direction of waves.
واتجاهات الامواج
Mau was, in fact,
"ماو " في الحقيقة
gathering explicit data
يجمع معلومات هائلة
using his entire body.
باستخدام جسده
It's what he had been trained to do
انه ما دُرب عليه
since he was five years old.
منذ كان عمره 5 سنوات
Now science may dismiss this methodology,
والان العلماء يهملون هذه المنهجية
but Polynesian navigators use it today
التي يستخدمها البحارة البولينيزين
because it provides them
لانه تؤمن لهم
an accurate determination
معلومات دقيقة
of the angle and direction
عن الزوايا والاتجاهات
of their vessel.
لزورقهم
The palu also had
وقبيلة "باولو " تملك ايضاً
an uncanny ability
قدرة خارقة
to forecast weather conditions
على التنبؤ بأحوال الطقس
days in advance.
لعدة ايام مقبلة
Sometimes I'd be with Mau on a cloud-covered night
واحيانا اكون مع " ماو " في ليلة ذات سماء غائمة
and we'd sit at the easternmost coast of the island,
واجلس بقربه على احد جروف الجزيرة قبل السفر
and he would look out,
فينظر هو الى السماء
and then he would say,
ومن ثم يقول
"Okay, we go."
" حسناً .. حان وقت الذهاب "
He saw that first glint of light --
انه يرى اول بصيص من الضوء
he knew what the weather was going to be three days from now.
وهو يعلم كيف سيكون الطقس في ال3 ايام القادمة
Their achievements, intellectually and scientifically,
ان انجازاتهم .. الفكرية والعلمية
are extraordinary,
مذهلة جداً
and they are so relevant
وهي هامة جداً
for these times that we are in
لهذه الاوقات التي نمر بها
when we are riding out storms.
التي تضربنا فيها العواصف
We are in such a critical moment
نحن في فترة عصيبة
of our collective history.
فيها خطرٌ على التاريخ متراكم
They have been compared
ان هؤلاء البحارة
to astronauts --
هم كما رواد الفضاء
these elder navigators
هؤلاء البحارة الكبار عمرا
who sail vast open oceans
الذين يبحرون في البحار الشاسعة
in double-hulled canoes
بواسطة زورق مزدوج
thousands of miles
لآلاف الاميال
from a small island.
من جزيرة صغيرة
Their canoes, our rockets;
ان زوارقهم تشابه .. مكوكات الفضاء خاصتنا
their sea, our space.
ان بحرهم ..يشابه فضاءنا
The wisdom of these elders
ان حكمة هؤلاء الاجداد
is not a mere collection
ليست مجرد تراكم علم
of stories about old people
من الاجداد
in some remote spot.
في مكان معزول
This is part of our collective narrative.
انها جزء من منحى تطور
It's humanity's DNA.
الحمض النووي للإنسانية (الدي ان ايه )
We cannot afford to lose it.
لا يمكننا ان نغامر بأن نخسرها
The year is 2010.
هذا هو عام 2010
Just as the women in Hawaii
وكإمرأة في هاواي
that raised me predicted,
هذا يدفعني لكي أتنبأ
the world is in trouble.
ان العالم في خطر
We live in a society
نحن نعيش في مجتمع
bloated with data,
مشبع بالمعلومات
yet starved for wisdom.
ولكنه فقير للحكمة
We're connected 24/7,
ونحن متصلون على مدى الساعة
yet anxiety,
فيما بيننا .. ولكننا رغم هذا قلقون
fear, depression and loneliness
خائفون .. محبطون .. وحيدون
is at an all-time high.
انه الوقت المناسب
We must course-correct.
لكي نغير منحى مجتمعنا
An African shaman said,
ذات يوم قال راهب أفريقي
"Your society worships the jester
" ان مجتمعك يقدس المهرج
while the king stands
ويترك الملك يقف
in plain clothes."
وحيداً "
The link between the past and the future
ان الرابط بين الماضي والحاضر
is fragile.
اصبح هشاً جداً
This I know intimately,
انا اعلم هذا جيداً ..
because even as I travel
لانه وعلى مدى سفري
throughout the world
حول العالم
to listen to these stories and record them,
لكي استمع للقصص واوثقها
I struggle.
انا اعاني ..
I am haunted
انا متخوفة
by the fact that I no longer remember
من فكرة انني قد لا اتذكر
the names of the winds and the rains.
اسماء الرياح والامطار
Mau passed away
لقد توفي " ماو "
five months ago,
منذ 5 اشهر
but his legacy and lessons live on.
ولكن ارثه ودروسه مازالت باقية
And I am reminded
وانا دوماً اذكر نفسي
that throughout the world
انه عبر العالم
there are cultures
هناك الكثير من الثقافات
with vast sums of knowledge in them,
تملك كماً من العلوم
as potent as the Micronesian navigators,
كما " البوتنيت " و كما " الميكروزيون "
that are going dismissed,
سوف تندثر
that this is a testament
ان هذه توصية \ تذكير
to brilliant, brilliant
بان هناك كم من الحكمة الخلابة
technology and science and wisdom
والعلوم الباهرة
that is vanishing rapidly.
تندثر بصورة متسارعة
Because when an elder dies a library is burned,
لانه في كل مرة يموت فيها رجل عجوز من تلك الثقافات .. تُحرق مكتبة كاملة
and throughout the world, libraries are ablaze.
وعبر عالمنا .. للاسف المكاتب تشتعلُ ناراً
I am grateful for the fact
انا في الحقيقة ممتنة جداً
that I had a mentor like Mau
لان شخص مثل "ماو" ارشدني
who taught me how to navigate.
وعلمني كيف ابحر .. واسير في هذا العالم
And I realize
وانا مدركة
through a lesson that he shared
عبر الدروس التي علمني إياها
that we continue to find our way.
اننا سوف نجد الطريق دوماً
And this is what he said:
وقد قال لي ذات يوم ..
"The island is the canoe;
ان الزورق هو الجزيرة ..
the canoe, the island."
والجزيرة هي الزورق "
And what he meant was,
وما عناه
if you are voyaging
انه ان كنت تبحر ..
and far from home,
بعيداً عن الوطن
your very survival depends
فإن نجاتك
on everyone aboard.
تعتمد على رفاقك في الابحار
You cannot make the voyage alone,
لايمكنك ان تبحر وحيداً
you were never meant to.
لم نخلق لذلك ..
This whole notion of every man for himself
ان الوطن هو كل فرد
is completely unsustainable.
والفردية لم تكن المغزى يوماً
It always was.
ولن تكون
So in closing I would offer you this:
وفي الختام اريد ان اقول لكم
The planet is our canoe,
الكوكب هو زورقنا
and we are the voyagers.
ونحن البحارة
True navigation
المستكشفون الحقيقيون
begins in the human heart.
وان نستدل على إبحارنا بقلوبنا البيضاء ..
It's the most important map of all.
لهو الاستدلال الامثل .. والخارطة الافضل
Together, may we journey well.
لنا جميعاً .. وأتمنى لنا جميعاً إبحارٌ ممتع
(Applause)
(تصفيق)